This video is sponsored by NordVPN. Stay
protected from online threats and
censorship. Get their 2-year plan plus
four extra months by using my link in
the description.
In 1968, American ethologist and
behavioral scientist John B. Calhoun
created a utopia.
A perfect world designed [music] for
well-being, reproduction, and longevity.
If you were a lucky enough mouse to be
one of the first to exist inside this
world, you experienced a kind of rodent
[music] heaven. Endless food, water, and
nesting resources, and a clean, stable,
well-designed large space with no
predators, no storms, and no diseases.
[music]
However, if you were a mouse born into
this utopia just a few generations
later, despite the space remaining
fundamentally unchanged, just as
bountiful, stable, and secure, you
experienced a kind of mouse hell.
After around 1 year, the population in
Calhoun's constructed habitat went from
eight mice to around a thousand. [music]
After 2 years, it rose to about 2,000.
Just two more years after that, all the
mice had died. Nothing changed about the
habitat or its conditions. Nothing was
introduced, nothing was taken away. It
was still fundamentally a mouse utopia.
The degeneration and extinction of the
mice came solely from the behavior of
the mice themselves.
This experiment is known as Universe 25.
As implied by the name, it wasn't the
first time Calhoun constructed a rodent
habitat. For decades leading up to
Universe 25 and following it, he
conducted many rodent-based experiments,
building out habitats and conditions,
and carefully monitoring and adjusting
variables within them. His initial aim
was to understand the behaviors of
rodents in various population densities
to assist [music] with pest management
in cities.
His research soon expanded and deepened,
however, as he began [music] to consider
and apply his findings to the management
of cities themselves, how humans
interact with each other in confined
spaces, and how population growth
affects both individual behavior [music]
and society at large.
He wrote,
"I shall largely speak of mice, but my
thoughts are on man, on healing, on life
and its evolution."
Around this time in the 1950s and '60s,
fears about global overpopulation and
its consequences were mounting.
Predictions were being made about mass
starvations and population crashes.
Deviancy and violence were in fact
already increasing in many modern cities
around this time. Many saw Calhoun's
work as representative, or at least
crucially insightful, to the conditions
humanity was facing and the possible
future it might face.
In 1954, Calhoun was hired by the
National Institute of Mental Health to
further advance his research.
Here, he began designing, building, and
studying elaborate rodent habitats,
which would be referred to as universes.
The 25th iteration, Universe 25, is by
far the most famous and culturally
enduring one, revealing unsettling
possibilities about social structures,
individual behavior, and how species can
self-destruct under apparently ideal
conditions.
The universe was a square enclosure 101
inches across, enclosed by 54-in tall
walls. Each wall had stairwells with
passageways branching off, leading to
nesting boxes. Each box contained enough
space to comfortably house 15 mice.
With 256 boxes in total, there was
enough comfortable nesting space
>> [music]
>> to house 3,840
mice in the whole universe.
The experiment started with eight
healthy, disease-free mice, four males
and four females.
As mentioned, they were given unlimited
food, water, and nesting materials. The
space was cleaned regularly, the
temperature was always perfect. There
were no predators or other environmental
uncertainties. The conditions were set
up to be ideal for life, and then
Calhoun and his team simply watched and
waited without any further adjustment.
What followed, however, just a few mice
generations later was anything but
ideal.
Over the course of just under 5 years,
Calhoun observed what he would describe
as four phases.
The first phase was the adjustment
phase.
Here, lasting just around 3 months, the
initial mice familiarized themselves
with the new environment, marked their
territory, and began nesting.
Then, the first pups were born.
Here, the second phase began.
The exploitation phase.
The new mice began mating and the
population began to increase rapidly,
doubling every 55 days.
In less than a year, there were more
than 600 mice. Still, food, water, and
nesting was plentiful.
But something strange soon began to
happen. The third phase.
The stagnation phase.
Population growth suddenly slowed. It
went from doubling every 55 days to
doubling approximately every 145.
Nearly three times slower.
Alongside the slowing, a sort of
complete behavioral breakdown began to
unfold. Random extreme violence, infant
mortality, asexuality, self-obsession,
and isolation.
Mice are inherently social creatures.
They have social hierarchies where males
establish their position through
fighting. The winners gain access to
multiple females and the losers often
retreat and move on to start over in
different territory.
Since there was no friction in the
universe, since everything was optimal
and easy and available, the population
increased rapidly and this meant there
was simultaneously an excess of mice to
compete and interact with, while there
was also no clear need for competition.
If food, water, space, and mating
partners are abundant, the point of
fighting becomes less clear.
Subsequently, social roles also become
unclear. Equally, if not more
importantly, mice become stuck in these
ambiguous social hierarchies with
nowhere to go. Where does a mouse go
that has lost a fight or found
themselves in a lower-ranked social
position when the walls around them
remain fixed?
There is no escaping the constant sense
of inferiority and overwhelm. This led
to extreme stress and anxiety, which
only further exacerbated the
dysfunction, soon causing the mice to
abandon social roles and ordinary
behavior altogether.
Many mice, particularly males, violently
lashed out toward other mice for no
apparent reason. It was as if the
impulse for aggression remained, but the
reasons and functions disappeared.
Likewise, since many males no longer
protected nests, females also became
hyper-defensive and aggressive,
sometimes even toward their own pups.
On the opposite end of the spectrum,
some mice simply gave up, receding from
the colony into isolation.
Calhoun referred to one male group
within this category [music]
as the beautiful ones, because all they
did besides eat and sleep was groom
themselves.
They avoided fights, avoided females and
sex, avoided interactions, avoided
everything except self-obsession.
Likewise, many females hid and isolated
in high-up nesting boxes, often
experiencing reduced fertility and
suppressed maternal instincts.
Ultimately, the mouse society broke
down.
They essentially forgot how to function
as mice. They stopped mating and started
dying.
On day 560 of the experiment, the mice
population peaked at 2,200 mice,
well over a thousand short of the actual
[music] capacity of the habitat.
Then, the final phase ensued,
the death phase.
Just under 5 years after the first eight
mice were placed inside, [music] after
thousands more had been born,
the last mouse
died.
The universe was lifeless.
Of course, there's a lot of interesting
things to consider and interpret here.
People in groups have been making
interpretations and taking away
conclusions from this experiment ever
since it was first published. Still to
this day, many people map and apply
phenomena from Universe 25 onto the
conditions of humanity. Admittedly, many
things have been and continue to be
eerily similar and reflective. Across
the 19th and 20th centuries, the global
human population saw massive
unprecedented increase as infant
mortality rates dropped. Several
generations later, right now, human
birth rates have sharply decreased.
Younger generations have seemed to
disengage from many ordinary social
protocols and timelines, having less sex
and forming fewer relationships.
Loneliness is at historically high
levels. Radicalization and polarization
across views and behaviors are also
concerningly high and increasing.
In terms of Calhoun and his team's
interpretations and conclusions,
>> [music]
>> they argued that in overpopulated
conditions, rodents experienced a
dramatic increase in pathological
behavior, which spreads and leads to
social breakdown. He referred to this
phenomenon as behavioral sink.
He and others like him applied these
findings onto human society, believing
that there is a tendency for social
animals to self-destruct when
overpopulating an environment. He saw
this as a possible encroaching risk for
humanity if we did not slow population
growth or overcome it through other
means.
In his paper, Death Squared, he wrote,
"For an animal so complex as man, there
is no logical reason why a comparable
sequence of events should not also lead
to species extinction. If opportunities
for role fulfillment fall far short of
the demand by those capable of filling
roles and having expectations to do so,
only violence and disruption of social
organization can follow.
Individuals born under these
circumstances will be so out of touch
with reality as to be in capable even of
alienation. Their most complex behaviors
will become fragmented. Acquisition,
creation, and utilization of ideas
appropriate for life in a
post-industrial, cultural, conceptual,
technological society will have been
blocked. Loss of these respective
complex behaviors means death of the
species."
Calhoun believed that as the global
population continued to increase into
the 21st century, we could reach a point
where there would be more people than
clear social roles and [music] physical
space. A solution, he argued, was
relying more on conceptual, non-physical
space. He believed that humans could
overcome the effects of overcrowding
through a kind [music] of creative
ingenuity, through technology and
abstract realms of culture.
The irony here is that, arguably,
something closer to the opposite has
[music] turned out to be the cause for
concern. Increasing global population
hasn't directly led to a decrease in
available [music] social roles, and it
isn't obvious what it has caused and how
much. Rather, what appears clearer is
that the increased [music] proliferation
of technology into every aspect of daily
life has made social roles, social
bonds, and cultural meaning harder to
discern, [music]
parse, form, and hold on to.
We have created our own kind of universe
25, not through diminishing physical
space, but by bringing the entire world
into our homes and minds. [music]
We exist now, in large part, in digital
and conceptual realms,
>> [music]
>> the internet, media, and the rapidly
spreading and shifting memes of culture.
What we seem to be left with isn't
[music] an escape from the overcrowding
of streets and physical space, but an
entryway for the overcrowding to enter
our every moment. We have confined
ourselves too close to each other,
addicted to the utopian access of
everything at all [music] times.
Neil Postman writes in Amusing Ourselves
to Death,
"Everything in our background has
prepared us [music] to know and resist a
prison when the gates begin to close
around us. But what if there are no
cries of anguish to be heard?
Who is prepared to take arms against a
sea of amusements? To whom do we
complain and when
>> [music]
>> and in what tone of voice when serious
discourse dissolves into giggles?
What is the antidote to a culture's
being drained [music] by laughter?"
We aren't built for this much
stimulation, this much social
interaction, this much competition and
comparison,
and this little structure and clarity.
We are bombarded constantly with brief,
isolated, meaningless information and
interactions.
They aren't even really interactions.
Much of our interactions with humans now
are simulations of interactions,
conversations we observe from behind a
one-sided screen, huddled alone in our
bed or on our couch. We feel the
register of social activity, of
humanity, but very little of the meaning
and resonance. Instead of competing with
our neighbors and communities while
we're together, we compete with the
whole world all the time. Even if we
don't participate in online culture or
social media or trends in general, we
likely observe them from afar, feeling
not so dissimilar from those who do
participate. Left out, confused,
overwhelmed, like we're losing some game
without any clear rules and undisclosed
prizes.
What this does and will all ultimately
equate to is impossible to say. But on
an individual level, it does seem to
already be leading to concerning
outcomes. Increased radicalization,
aggressiveness, numbness to violence,
extreme ideologies, or receding into
social isolation, apathy, a sense of
deviance, a disengagement from social
activity. According to global indexes,
the world is seeing rising political
extremism. At the same time, based on a
national survey conducted by Harvard,
over 20% of adults report feeling lonely
frequently or all the time, with that
number rising to around 30% in midlife.
Most surveyed individuals say that
technology is a contributing factor.
One thing Calhoun discovered that is
often ignored in discussions of his work
is that in Universe 25, as well as in
other experiments,
he noticed that some deviant behaviors
in mice actually proved to be a good
thing.
For example, he noticed that a certain
group of males dug burrows in a specific
way to reduce [music] social contact.
But the method turned out to be more
efficient and functional because they
consolidated the process [music] by
packing and removing dirt in fewer
trips.
Of course, deviance isn't always going
to lead to good things or greater
effectiveness, but the point is, perhaps
turning some amount away from the
existing conditions and protocols of a
society may not always be a bad thing.
Perhaps the mice who separated
themselves, at least on some level, were
actually pursuing the best of the
possible situations, even if all
situations [music] weren't ideal.
In the words of Jiddu Krishnamurti,
is society healthy that an individual
should return to it? Has not society
itself [music] helped to make the
individual unhealthy? Of course, the
unhealthy must be made healthy. That
goes without saying. But why should the
individual adjust himself to an
unhealthy society?
If he is healthy, he will not be a part
of it.
Without first questioning the health of
society, what is the good of helping
misfits to conform to society?
Of course, the goal is arguably always
social connection and contributing to a
functional society, but perhaps
removing, or at least distancing oneself
from it,
>> [music]
>> at least at times and in intentional
ways, is actually the best means toward
these goals.
Perhaps it's the best of the possible
situations, [music] even if all aren't
ideal.
Ultimately, it isn't obvious what and
how much should be taken from Universe
25, as well as Calhoun's work in
general. Both are highly critiqued and
widely misinterpreted. And crucially, we
aren't mice. Even if we share some
behavioral similarities,
>> [music]
>> what kinds and how much is unclear.
And so, the superimpositions of lessons
and morals drawn from mice onto humans
[music] is, at the very least, worth
seriously questioning.
In the end, the mice couldn't escape
their world.
>> [music]
>> And in many ways, we can't, either.
But unlike the mice, we can be more
intentional. We can think, reflect, and
question.
Perhaps we can find a kind of escape,
not through leaping over walls, but
leaping over standards [music] and
expectations. Over preconceived answers,
over blindly prescribed ideas and norms.
If we want clarity, perhaps it starts
[music] in the burrows we dig for
ourselves.
In the words of Albert Camus,
in order to understand the world, one
has to turn away from it on occasion.
In order to serve men better,
one has to hold them at a distance for a
time.
Our lives inevitably rely on the
internet now. There's no denying that.
The internet undeniably provides immense
opportunity and value. The most
important thing we can do, however, is
simply be intentional with our online
presence and how we engage with it. This
also includes protecting ourselves from
cyber threats like privacy breaches,
fraud, phishing, malware, and other dark
web activities. This video's sponsor,
NordVPN, is like creating your own
secure digital nesting box, protecting
yourself from the predatory and hostile
aspects of the online environment all
with just a couple clicks.
Whether you're at home, traveling, or
connected to public Wi-Fi, NordVPN
encrypts your online traffic and keeps
your browsing private and secure.
Not only is NordVPN the fastest VPN and
one of the most feature-rich overall,
it's also the only VPN officially
certified by independent testers
recognized by leading cybersecurity
labs. As a certified phishing protection
tool, its threat protection pro detects
nearly all phishing websites and
automatically blocks any attempts to
steal sensitive information. It also
automatically blocks dangerous ads and
prevents malware from getting to you via
websites [music] and files. And NordVPN
extends to things you're not even aware
of, like your data being leaked or
hacked. In the background, NordVPN's
dark web monitor constantly scans
websites, catches if your data is being
used or sold, [music] and notifies you
immediately. With NordVPN, your data and
online activity are protected, [music]
allowing you to stay connected without
falling victim to the chaos. Go to
nordvpn.com/pursuitofwonder
or click the link in the description
[music]
to get your 2-year plan plus four extra
months. It comes with a 30-day
money-back guarantee, [music] so it's a
no-brainer to try.
And of course, as always, thank you so
much for watching in general,
and see you next video.